Davida Foy Crabtree papers, 1883-2022.
Congregational Library & Archives
Davida Foy Crabtree papers, 1883-2022.
MS5324
Congregational Library & Archives
4.71 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
Davida Foy was born in 1944 to Davida and Alfred Foy. She attended Marietta College in Ohio from 1963-1967, followed by Andover Newton Theological School from 1968-1972. She became the director of the Prudence Crandall Center for Women (PCCW) in New Britain, Connecticut. In 1980, she was called to serve the Colchester Federated Church in Connecticut, where she served for 11 years. She took on the role of conference minister for the UCC's Southern California Conference until she returned to serve as Connecticut's conference minister in 1996. She retired from that position in 2010. The collection includes personal and professional writing, academic work, sermons, correspondence, and records generated as part of Crabtree's ministerial work.
Crabtree, Davida Foy
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Davida Foy Crabtree in January 2017; accession 2017-01. Additional materials were donated in January 2024 (accession 2024-02) and March 2025 (accession 2025-07).
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Biographical / Historical
Davida Foy was born in 1944 to Davida and Alfred Foy. She attended Litchfield High School and was active as a teenager with the newly-formed United Church of Christ's statewide youth Pilgrim Fellowship. She served as editor for their publication, Yankee Reporter. After graduating, she attended Marietta College in Ohio from 1963-1967, followed by Andover Newton Theological School from 1968-1972. She married Robert Crabtree in 1968 while still in seminary. Both trained for the Peace Corps in Libya but didn't go before completing their work at Andover Newton.
As a student in the late 1960s and early 1970s, she was deeply involved in the social change movements prevalent to this era. Much of the material she retained for this collection includes articles about social and political events and her involvement in them. Crabtree's focus as a young adult centered on spirituality, religion, and feminism. She blended this work as the director of the Prudence Crandall Center for Women (PCCW) in New Britain, Connecticut. While working as campus minister at Central Connecticut State University, Crabtree saw a pressing need for a women's center and so founded PCCW to provide a haven for those living through domestic violence. During this time, she also served on the United Church of Christ's Executive Council where she also championed women's issues.
In 1980, she was called to serve the Colchester Federated Church in Connecticut, where she served for 11 years. She married David T. Hindinger in 1982, becoming stepmother to his two children, Elizabeth and Todd. While serving Colchester, she attended Hartford Seminary for her Doctor of Ministry degree. Following her tenure at Colchester, she took on the role of conference minister for the UCC's Southern California Conference until she returned to serve as Connecticut's conference minister in 1996. Crabtree retired from the post in 2010. Following that, she has served as senior consultant to the officers of the national UCC (2011-13); interim senior advancement officer for Andover Newton (2011); acting conference minister for Missouri Midsouth Conference (2013); interim conference minister for Florida Conference (2013-2014); and interim vice president for institutional advancement at Andover Newton (2016-2017).
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of the personal paper of Davida Foy Crabtree. The collection includes personal writing and professional writing, academic work, sermons, correspondence, calendars, articles and newsletters pertaining to Crabtree's career, records related to advocacy and activism, United Church of Christ committee records, and records generated while working for the Prudence Crandall Center for Women, the Connecticut Conference of the UCC, the Southern California Conference of the UCC, and the Colchester Federated Church in Connecticut.
Arrangement
The original order of the collection was strictly chronological. During processing, some divisions were made to indicate topic or subject, however the order remains in chronological order.
Feminism -- Religious aspects.; Sermons, American.; Clergy -- Correspondence.; World Council of Churches.; Andover Newton Theological School
- Antoinette Brown Blackwell signature, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Annette Gray records, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions missionary vessel certificate, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Childhood, academic and personal writing, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Pilgrim Fellowship, Yankee Reporter, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Diary, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
- Diary, 1961 (Box 5)
- Correspondence and personal writing, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Magazine and newspaper articles, 1961 1982; 1961-1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Yearbook, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Marietta College, general and academic work, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Calendars, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and personal writing, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Book reviews and correspondence, 1967 2007; 1967-2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Andover Newton Theological Seminary academic work, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Davida and Robert Crabtree wedding, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Church and activism with related newsletters and articles, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- United Churchmen for Change, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Calendars, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Activism, activities, correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Newsletters, articles, current events, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Community organizing project, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Women's caucus, Massachusetts Conference UCC, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- UCC Synod, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Activism, activities, correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- World Council of Christian Education (WCCE) World Assembly, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Women Exploring Theology at Grailville, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Calendars, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Newsletters, articles, current events, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Activism, activities, correspondence, including ordination, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
- Task force on women in church and society, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Planning and correlation committee records, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Newsletters, articles, including installation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Paulo Freire- Learning and change workshop, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Activities, correspondence, including installation, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Planning and correlation committee oft he executive council, UCC, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- National Council of Churches board analysis, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Prudence Crandall Center for Women, New Beginnings, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Prudence Crandall Center for Women (PCCW) records, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Activities, writings, correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- PCCW- "Bottled Up Woman" - alcoholism and women, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Outrage service, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- UCC - Advisory committee on women, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Women in the city course material and notes, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Prudence Crandal Center for Women, recognition, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Activities, writing, correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Newsletters, articles, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Robert V. Moss, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Personnel committee- executive council, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Overseas seminar, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Rajendra (Raju) K. Sail, 1970s-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Calendars, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Activities, writings, correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
- Leadership development, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Activities, writings, correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- United Church of Christ advisory commission on woman artwork, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Newsletters, articles, current events, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Diary, 1979 1982; 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Inclusive language, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
- Calendars, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Activities, writings, correspondence, including installation at Colchester, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence including marriage to David Hindiger, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Addresses, prayers, and sermons, 1982 2022; 1982-2022 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10-13)
- Doctor of ministry, Hartford Seminary, papers, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Calendars, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
- East Africa seminar, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Implications of development for parish ministry, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Re-imagining Redemption Symposium essays, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Life Styles Inventory self development guide and test results, circa 1989 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Calendars, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence including S. California Conference Minister work, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Conference work, sermons, correspondence, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- El Salvador delegation, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Personal career development profile, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondenceActivities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Calendars, 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Connecticut Conference Minister, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Growing in Authority, Cecelia Hahn, interview and book, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Calendars, 1997-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Calendars, 2000-2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Colombia delegation, CT Conference, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Calendars, 2005-2012 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, Colombia delegation, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- UCC 50th anniversary, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Activities, writings, sermons, correspondence, 2008-2009 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Activities, writing, correspondence, including David Hindinger's death, 2009-2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Retirement celebration, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Activities, writing, correspondence, 2010-2013 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- 19th Antoinetter Brown Award presentation booklet, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Andover Newton archives donation, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Activities, writing, correspondence, 2014-2016 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Annotated index to collection written by Crabtree, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pins and medalions, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- A prayer for the installation of Davida Foy Crabtree, undated (Folder 7)